קפג עמוד ב, Kuf Yod Gimmel Amud Bet, again קפד Kuf Yod
Dalet picking up on דף קפג עמוד ב, Daf Kuf Yod Gimmel
Amud Bet, five lines from the bottom, the two dots. We are,
we were dealing with the issue about changing clothes for שבת Shabbat
based on a משנה Mishnah that talked about folding your clothes, talked
about certain איסורים issurim but it gave us the opportunity to really
focus and introduce the issue of כבוד שבת Kavod Shabbat and talking
about extraneous matters, changing your clothes, and so on, various range of
different activities or not doing activities for כבוד שבת. Kavod Shabbat. Because
of the emphasis on כבוד kavod and clothes being considered something that
gives honor, we have the following דרשה: drasha: ותחת כבדו יקד יקד
כיקד אש. Vesachas kvodo yekad yekod kikod esh. And underneath his כבוד
kavod was a burning fire, was like burning like the burning of
fire. So what does this mean? אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan:
ותחת כבדו ולא כבדו ממש. Vesachas kvodo velo kvodo mamash. Underneath the
כבוד kavod and not the כבוד kavod itself. רש"י Rashi says this
is because the same מן דאמר man d'amar who argued before, I
actually think that this is talking because of the emphasis of the
כבוד. kavod. And this is talking about, who's it talking about? One
minute, I'm sorry. סנחריב, Sancheiriv, yes, thank you, talking about סנחריב. Sancheiriv.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, so what is this כבודו?
kvodo? אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: ותחת כבדו ולא כבדו ממש.
Vesachas kvodo velo kvodo mamash. Underneath the כבוד kavod and not the
כבוד kavod itself. רש"י Rashi says this means that the burning was
like the bodies burnt and it burned underneath the clothes but the
clothes did not burn. This is when the army of סנחריב Sancheiriv
was wiped out. רבי יוחנן לטעמיה, Rabbi Yochanan l'taimei, רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan goes by his reasoning, דאמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, as
we learned yesterday,
רבי יוחנן קרי למאני מכבדותי. Rabbi Yochanan karei l'manei mechabdisai. As we
learned yesterday, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan calls his clothes the things that
honor me, מכבדותי. mechabdisai. So that's why it is he's able to
read that they were burnt, their bodies were burnt and not their
clothes. רבי אלעזר אומר: Rabbi Elazar omer: ותחת כבדו ותחת כבדו ממש.
Vesachas kvodo, tachas kvodo mamash. So it means that he understands that
the word כבודו kvodo means actually the person himself. So he says
that the person himself and what does it mean to burn under
the person? I mean how do you have a burning that's underneath
the person himself, like in the person himself? So it means that
the souls were destroyed, the life was destroyed, but the body remained.
רבי ישמעאל בר נחמני, Rabbi Yishmael bar Nachmani, so that's כבודו ממש.
kvodo mamash. רבי ישמעאל בר נחמני אמר: Rabbi Yishmael bar Nachmani amar:
ותחת כבדו כשרפת בני אהרן. Vesachas kvodo kishreifat b'nei Aharon. מה להלן
שרפת נשמה וגוף קיים אף כאן שרפת נשמה וגוף קיים. Mah lelan
sreifat neshama veguf kayam af kan sreifat neshama veguf kayam. Actually, I'm
sorry, I skipped ahead. That was רבי ישמעאל בר נחמני. Rabbi Yishmael
bar Nachmani. רבי ישמעאל בר נחמני Rabbi Yishmael bar Nachmani says that
it means under the כבוד, kavod, meaning רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says
ותחת כבדו tachas kvodo means the כבוד kavod means the body, but
ותחת כבדו tachas kvodo means like the body was destroyed, whereas רבי
ישמעאל בר נחמני Rabbi Yishmael bar Nachmani says no, כבודו kvodo means
the body and ותחת tachas means from underneath or within the body,
so the body was retained and the soul was destroyed. All right
anyway, various range of דרשות drashot that tie into the idea of
כבוד kavod referring to one's clothes at least according to רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. All right so now the גמרא Gemara continues, אמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan: מנין לשינוי בגדים מן התורה? Minayin l'shinnui bgadim min HaTorah?
Back again to clothes, again with רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. How do
we know that the changing of clothes מן התורה? min HaTorah? That
we have a biblical hint of the idea. Like we quoted before
the idea about ורחצת וסכת v'rachatzat v'sacht was your clothes by Ruth,
put on your שמלתיך, simlotayich, these are בגדי שבת. bgadei Shabbat. Where
else do you have this idea from the התורה Torah that changing
clothes, it's an appropriate way to show honor, how you dress for
different circumstances and changing to nicer clothes for certain and other clothes
for other circumstances? שנאמר Shene'emar because it says by the עבודה avoda
of taking out the ashes in the בית המקדש: Beit HaMikdash: ופשט
את בגדיו ולבש בגדים אחרים. upashat et bgadav v'lavash bgadim acherim. You
should take off your clothes and wear other clothes to take out
the ashes. So the דרשה drasha is, ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל: v'tana
d'bei Rabbi Yishmael: למדתך תורה דרך ארץ. limadcha Torah derech eretz. התורה
Torah is teaching you a proper way of behaving. בגדים שבישל בהן
קדירה לרבו אל ימזוג בהן כוס לרבו. bgadim shebishal bahen kedera l'rabo
al yimzug bahen kos l'rabo. The clothes that you used to cook
the pot you should not use to serve the food, right? So
you put on your apron or you put on certain clothes while
you're cooking, you put on other clothes when you're actually attending, coming
to dinner or serving the dinner and when you are presenting yourself
in a certain way. So again an indication it's not like some
clothes are bad and some clothes are good, but clothes should be
appropriate for the occasion and therefore if you want to show particular
honor for שבת, Shabbat, then you dress in a certain way that
is respectful and shows the respect for שבת. Shabbat. Okay. אמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan: גנאי הוא... gnai hu... now that we're talking about clothes
and how you wear, the גמרא Gemara is going to shift to
it's not only wearing different clothes for certain types of occasions, but
also just how one, even whatever clothes one is wearing, how one
appears and how one takes care of their appearance and the appearance
of their clothes no matter how fancy or plain they are. אמר
רבי חייא בר אבא... Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba... how one wears
and the גמרא Gemara is going to shift to, it's not only
wearing different clothes for certain types of occasions, but also just how
one, even whatever clothes one is wearing, how one appears and how
one takes care of their appearance and the appearance of their clothes,
no matter how fancy or plain they are. So אמר רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi
Yochanan, again a statement in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
גנאי הוא לתלמיד חכם שיצא במנעלים המטולאים, gnay hu letalmid chacham sheyeitzei
biminalim hametulaim, it is a גנאי, gnay, what's a good word for
גנאי? gnay? An embarrassment, disgrace, thank you, it's a disgrace for a
Torah scholar to go out with shoes that have patches on them.
You know, you don't have to wear expensive shoes, but you shouldn't
wear things that look, you know, that look like you're in, that
look like, you know, you're in tatters. What? Unpolished shoes? Well, we'll
get to something like that in a minute. Anyway, לשוק, lashuk, to
the marketplace, because you represent Torah and you have to, you should
not make the Torah look, you know, bad and disgraceful in the
eyes of people. So the גמרא Gemara says והא רבי חייא בר
חנינא נפיק? veha Rabbi Chiyya bar Chanina nafik? One minute, Rabbi Chiyya
bar Chanina went out with shoes with, that had patches on them!
So אמר רבי אבא בריה דרב נחמן: Amar Rabbi Abba brei deRav
Nachman: טלאי על גב טלאי. telai al gav telai. No, the only
problem is when your patches have patches, right? That's like a saying,
right? He's so poor that his patches have patches. So right, you
could say look, you know, look, the person is poor, what are
they supposed to do, right? And they don't always have an option
of okay, well we don't, you know, buy inexpensive shoes or I
can't even afford inexpensive shoes, I can only, so you know, I
don't exactly, I don't have an answer for what do you deal
with the fact that, you know, a person, how's a person supposed
to pay for it if he doesn't have the money, although we
will talk a little bit later about the community helping support a
תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, which we'll get to, which we'll get to
that, don't worry, we'll get to that, that'll be a little later.
But you know what I would say is and this gets to
the whole issue, I mean it's funny also the גמרא Gemara speaking
about clothes, switching clothes, and you know, כתנת פסים, ketonet passim, יוסף,
Yosef, וחליפות שמלות, vechalifot semalot, but anyway, and mentions the כהן kohen
serving the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash because clearly the
emphasis on בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna talks
about the importance of the clothes you wear and what type of
an image they project. Now part of the problem though is, you
know, and this is the whole issues around the כהונה kehuna and
the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna and מומים mumim in particular, you know,
clearly presents this challenge because it is true that people like, you
know, make sort of judgments based on externals, but you know, but
that doesn't always represent, you know, האדם יראה לעיניים והשם יראה ללבב,
ha'adam yireh la'einayim v'Hashem yireh lalivav, you know, so does that really
represent the true essence and the true value of the person? But
nevertheless, you know, we live in a real world and we live
in society where people make certain judgments and things create certain types
of impressions. So that I think is look, you know, what's going
on here. It might be true the guy can't afford anything else,
but what are you going to do if by the way you're
dressing, you know, it's there's just a reality that people are not
so big, you know, are not so generous minded and you know,
and they'll see this and it'll make them think very poorly of
Torah sages and about what Torah's all about. It's safe to say
somebody like the Dalai Lama or Gandhi, they in essence really overcame,
it didn't matter that they're wearing... yeah, but I think also, I
think that it also works on also cultivating cultural norms and educating
people towards that. Here we're just accommodating them, right. I understand, like
I said, I think that's a problem, I think it goes all
the way back to the issue of the כהנים kohanim and how
they dress and the מומים mumim and so on, how much you
sort of pander to or at least accommodate the certain norms and
how much you work to try to you know, change... You're actually
cultivating... Right, I agree, it's a problem, it's a problem, but in
the interim before people have changed, all right... why would he wear...
all right, we're moving on, we're moving on, but we've said what
the problem is. Okay, we know what the problem is.
Before people have changed, it's an issue. The question is how do
you get people to change. So now the גמרא Gemara moves on.
ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, ve'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל תלמיד חכם שנמצא רבב על בגדו, kol
talmid chacham shenimtza revav al bigdo,
here any Torah sage that has a stain like particularly just as
like a grease stain, something that really looks like you know, you
know, like disgusting and not just a spot or whatever, חייב מיתה,
chayav mita, goes out, you're deserving of
death, very harsh
language, שנאמר, shenemar, as the פסוק pasuk says, כל משנאי
אהבו מות,
kol
mesan'ai
ahavu mavet, all those
who hate me love death, אל תקרי משנאי אלא משניאי, al tikrei
mesan'ai ella mashni'ai, don't read who hate me, but mashni'ai who cause
others to hate me. So again, you represent Torah and if you
dress in a way that people say 'ech, it's disgusting,' then you
actually have done a terrible a terrible thing towards you know, people's
impression of Torah.
So again here at least maybe it's something
that you could do something more about, you could launder your clothes,
but you know what, laundry also costs money.
So what yeah, anyway but here is
the issue about how you dress, you know, it says something about
the respect that you're showing towards the environ- towards the people you're
with, towards the circumstance you're in, towards yourself, it also affects the
respect that other people give to you and towards what and towards
what you represent. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues, רבינא אמר
רבד איתמר, Ravina amar revad itmar, wasn't said רבב. revav. רבב, Ravav,
which is a grease stain, but רובד, Revvad, which is something worse.
What is it that's worse? רש״י Rashi actually says that this actually
is a semen stain. ולא פליגי V'lo pligi and they don't argue,
meaning you know it sounds like he would say a normal grease
stain would be okay. הא בגלימא הא בלבושא. Ha b'glima ha b'levusha.
One is your inner garment which is not so visible and the
other is your outer garment. So, so רש״י Rashi says if the
inner garment not so visible there we could tolerate a normal grease
stain, but we wouldn't obviously tolerate a semen stain. Okay. ואמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן V'amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan מאי דכתיב, mai dichsiv, what's meant by the פסוק pasuk
כאשר הלך עבדי ישעיהו ערום ויחף, Ka'asher halach avdi Yeshayahu arom v'yachef,
like my servant Isaiah walked naked and barefoot? ערום Arom doesn't mean
literally naked, it means בבגדים בלואים b'v'gadim bluyim with like garments in
tatters. ויחף V'yachef barefoot במנעלים המטולאים b'minalim hamutlaim again with with patched
up shoes. So again underscoring the point that these things are you
know are perceived of as you're really not properly clothed, it's almost
as if you're not wearing clothes. תנן התם Tnan hatam we taught
over there: רבב על המרדע revav al hamarda if you have this
grease stain on a saddle, חוצץ chotzetz that's a חציצה. chatzitza. So
obviously it's not just a totally absorbed grease stain, there's actually some
surface grease on it. If it was totally absorbed, then it would
not be that case, but anyway there's some surface grease, it's a
חציצה chatzitza because now רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
so again you know that general people, טבילה t'vila yeah for טומאה
וטהרה tumah v'tahara you want to make your טהור tahor saddle, a
זב zav sat on the saddle. So it shows also that people
are מקפיד machpid because the only thing that's חוצץ chotzetz is something
that people are מקפיד. machpid. So again it ties into the idea
that people really don't tolerate these types of stains on their garment.
Okay, where were we? חוצץ. Chotzetz. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer עד איסרי טלקי ad issari talki only if
it's an איסר טלקי issar talki the size of an Italian איסר
issar or bigger, only then is it a problem. Although the phrase
עד ad is a funny phrase but okay because it makes it
sound like like bigger than that isn't a problem but anyway presumably
it means smaller than that isn't a problem. ועל הבגדים מצד אחד
V'al hab'gadim mitzad echad if you have a grease stain on your
clothes if it's only on one side of the clothes אינו חוצץ,
eino chotzetz, it's not a חציצה. chatzitza. משני צדדים Me'shnei tzdadim if
it went got so absorbed that it's now visible on the other
side as well then חוצץ chotzetz then that is a חציצה. chatzitza.
רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer משום רבי ישמעאל mishum Rabbi Yishmael
אפילו מצד אחד חוצץ apilu mitzad echad chotzetz even from one side
it's a חציצה. chatzitza. Okay. בעי מיניה רבי שמעון בן לקיש מרבי
חנינא Ba'ei minei Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish me'Rabbi Chanina מרדע marda when
we spoke about the saddle and we said it was a problem,
what were we talking about? מצד אחד או משני צדדים Mitzad echad
o mi'shnei tzdadim one side or two sides? Now again I don't
know enough of that saddles or whatnot but to have a stain
heavy enough to go through from one side to the other to
the saddle to go on both sides it's got to be a
pretty heavy stain unless maybe we're talking about some like saddle saddle
blanket and not literally the saddle although מרדע marda normally means a
saddle. What? They're pretty heavy saddle blankets usually. Yeah. So yeah, so
I don't know it's got to be a pretty heavy stain but
look if we said two sides by clothes maybe we should say
it by saddles. So אמר ליה amar lei זו לא שמעתי zu
lo shamati you know what I haven't heard explicitly a tradition about
this. But כיוצא בה שמעתי k'yotze bah shamati I've heard a similar
a similar teaching. תנן כמאן משנה Tnan k'man mishna רבי יוסי אומר
Rabbi Yosi omer הבנאים hab'nayim which literally means builders, מצד אחד mitzad
echad there one side is already a problem. Meaning as opposed to
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that said that by clothes it always
is only a problem if it goes through side to side. He
says it depends whose clothes. בנאים Benayim clothes one side's a problem,
שבור shobur and an ignoramus like משני צדדים me'shnei tzdadim then only
from side to side is a problem. So how are you contrasting
בנאים benayim builders to a to an ignoramus? So we're going to
see in a minute that the גמרא Gemara assumes בנאים benayim here
refers to תורה Torah scholars like אל תקרי בנייך אלא בונייך al
tikri banayich ella bonayich although there actually בונייך bonayich is exactly what
it's saying. People that somehow build the right, בונייך אלא בונייך bonayich
ella bonayich anyway בנייך אלא בונייך banayich ella bonayich no that is
the same דרש, dhash, right? אל תקרי בנייך אלא בונייך Al tikri
banayich ella bonayich so the people who somehow build the world with
their תורה. Torah. So therefore again this idea that תורה תורה Torah
Torah scholars have to be more careful about their clothes because of
what they represent. So for them even on one side it's a
problem, but other people it's only a problem when it's two sides.
ולא תהא מרדע חשובה מבגדו של עם הארץ V'lo tihye marda chashuva
mi'bigdo shel am ha'aretz so look if normal people's clothes is only
you know not so sage it's only from you know it's only
from side to side, so therefore a saddle
should not be more significant than that.
So presumably saying that even a saddle it's only a problem if
it goes from one side to the next which has got to
be a pretty darn thick stain. So I don't know what to
tell you. But okay, fine. So now the גמרא Gemara says continues,
one minute, right. It's also funny why it had to quote רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi because why didn't it just quote the first opinion
that just said normal clothes are from two sides, you know and
you could say לא תהא lo tihye a saddle more חמור chamur
than that? But okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. מאי בנאים?
Mai Banayim? What are these בנאים? Banayim? אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rebbe
Yochanan: אלו תלמידי חכמים Elu Talmidei Chachamim שעוסקים בבנינו של עולם she'oskim
bevinyano shel olam כל ימיהם. kol yimeihem. These are Torah sages that
are engaged in the in in constructing the world for their entire
lives, right? It's probably, you know, for most people that's a somewhat
ironic statement, right? Other people go out and actually, you know, are
doctors and and lawyers and whatever and, well, I guess lawyers is
debatable, that's that old joke. By the way, you know the joke?
You know the joke? Constructing worlds, you know the joke that they're
having a whole debate about what was the first profession in the
world? So the surgeon says, you know, was surgery when, you know,
God did surgery on אדם הראשון. Adam HaRishon. And then, you know,
the whatever, you know, the electrician says, you know, whatever, you know,
said it was light, you know, it was being an electrician when
God brought light to the world. And then the architect said it
was architecture when God, you know, when God created, you know, when
God created the whole world initially. And then the lawyer says, and
who do you think brought the תוהו ובוהו? Tohu vaVohu? So anyway,
all right, so all right, we shouldn't start telling lawyer jokes. Anyway,
some of my best friends are lawyers. Anyway, so I'm really sorry,
that was a terrible digression. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara back to
this. So the גמרא Gemara really, you know, sort of to counter,
you know, what might be a this, you know, this perception from
the non-Torah world that, you know, they're just sitting and wasting their
time, really emphasizes, no, they're like building, you know, they are they
are spending their lives building the world. So that's the בנאים. Banayim.
And so now the גמרא Gemara continues: ואמר רבי יוחנן, ve-amar Rebbe
Yochanan, איזהו תלמיד חכם eizehu talmid chacham שמחזירין לו אבידה she-machzirin lo
aveidah בטביעות העין? bitvi'at ha-ayin? Now, who is a type of a
Torah sage? Now we're going to focus a little bit on Torah
sages, Torah scholars. So what is the type of a Torah scholar
that, by the way, תלמיד חכם talmid chacham does not mean nowadays
like תלמיד חכם talmid chacham they say, oh my God, that guy's
such a גדול, gadol, such a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, but תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham actually was a people that were still students of
the חכמים. chachamim. So they were like they were תלמיד, talmid, תלמיד
talmid of a חכם, chacham, right? תלמידי, talmidei, right. So anyway, so
so okay, but they're still spending all their time sitting and learning,
you know, they're not yet the חכם, chacham, but they're spending all
their time sitting and learning. So who is a תלמיד חכם שמחזירין
לו אבידה בטביעות העין? talmid chacham she-machzirin lo aveidah bitvi'at ha-ayin? That
you can have enough trust in their honesty, their integrity, that even
if they can't give a particular סימן siman to an אבידה, aveidah,
right? If you lost some type of an object, you might not
be able to describe, oh yes, it's got a mark exactly right
over here, but yes, if you saw it, you would recognize it
as your own. So is that sufficient? If I go and say,
you know, okay, fine, I guess I'm in a particular mood today,
I knew a friend at once said that he was he you
know he needed an umbrella and he didn't want to buy one
so he went over to the MTA, you know, their lost and
found and he said, I lost an umbrella. So the guy picked
a random umbrella somewhere and he said, is this it? He said,
yes! And he took it and went out. Anyway, so you know
you can lose your umbrella and not be able to describe it,
but you would recognize it. So obviously you can't return אבידות aveidahs
based on that, then anybody could claim something is theirs. But the
גמרא Gemara says that if it's a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, somebody
you can really trust their integrity, then you can return an אבידה
aveidah just if they say they recognize it. So what would what
type of a person would we say falls into this category? So
זה המקפיד על חלוקו להופכו. zeh hamakpid al chaluko l'hafcho. That's somebody
that is so careful about, you know, about how they present themselves
and, you know, not just, you know, and sort of and about
their own, I guess, you know, they're self-aware that even if they,
for example, put on their garments inside out, they'll take the time
to bother to take it off and to reverse it so it
looks proper. You don't have to be a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
meaning apparently, but but it's right, it's an interesting point in general,
you know, A: the assumption that, you know, that we would hope,
but, you know, sadly is not always the case, but that we
would hope that people devoting their lives to learning Torah leads to
a greater focus on מדות middot and character and honesty and integrity.
And number two, though, the idea that somehow there's a connection here
with how they how one presents oneself or is aware of how
one appears to other people as tied into that issue. You know,
obviously there are a lot of people that that are very they're
very careful on how they present themselves to other people and they
would דווקא davka want to look in a way that looks very
פרום frum or that looks like the way like a ישיבה yeshiva
guy looks or whatever, but that's, you know, but that doesn't reflect
a lot of else about who they are. You know, I'm not,
you know, whatever, that phenomenon exists, I'm not saying widespread, but the
phenomenon does exist. So it is interesting the assumption here that this
issue about being careful about outside perception, again part of part of
how you how you represent yourself to other people is your integrity
also determines about how other people, you know, see you and how
you act, etc. But he's clever and very vain and really cares.
I understand. I, well, that's why it adds it to this idea
of being a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, but again the sort of
combination of assumptions here is quite fascinating. Yeah, the assumption that one
is going to ascribe it to integrity to you because you... dress
a certain way? And all I can think of is those rabbis
in New Jersey who were led out in handcuffs for fraud but
with the ציצית. tzitzit. Right. Well that's sort of what I was
alluding to. You know so people could be very careful about the
perception that they give without actually you know and actually it can
serve as a mask towards other types of behavior. So yeah it's
not unique to Jews not unique to yeah I mean it's it's
just about being a person you know or honest for politicians some
of them were the worst bribe takers of all. Exactly. So yes
yes. So it's right it's just part of about the range of
human behavior but anyway it is interesting the combination here that the
גמרא Gemara makes. Elsewhere the גמרא Gemara talks about some about something
which we see much more relevant which is some which is somebody
that you know never misrepresents never is משנה בדיבורו meshaneh b'diburo never
you know even you know except the גמרא Gemara actually mentions like
three things that you're allowed to actually not give the full truth
about you know the white lies. But somebody that outside of those
you know you know has never said anything untrue. That makes a
lot more sense to be a measure of this type of an
issue. If you didn't know he was a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
and he did these things exactly exactly. You wouldn't necessarily know. Right
well you know every day he goes to ישיבה. yeshiva. Alright anyways
now the גמרא Gemara continues. ואמר רבי יוחנן v'amar Rabbi Yochanan so
Rabbi Yochanan also says איזהו תלמיד חכם שממנין אותו פרנס על הציבור.
eizehu talmid chacham she-memanin oto parnas al ha-tzibbur. Who is the Torah
scholar that you would actually be prepared to appoint him a you
know a some type of a position of responsibility over over the
community. So the idea of פרנס parnas is interesting because you know
normally פרנסים parnasim are exactly not the not the rabbis. The פרנסים
parnasim are the ones that go out and make the money and
then have the wealth to help you know or have positions of
lay leadership is usually what פרנס parnas is.
But here presumably it does mean
you know what is the type of person that a community would
be prepared to hire them as his rabbi you know presumably it
does mean in in his rabbinic capacity not necessarily as a
lay leader although פרנס parnas often does mean a lay leader. זה
ששואלין אותו דבר הלכה בכל מקום ואומר. ze she-sholin oto d'var halacha
b'chol makom v'omer. This is somebody that you can ask them a
halachic question from anywhere ואומר v'omer and he can tell you. He
would know right off
the spot ואפילו במסכת כלה va'afilu b'masechet kallah the right even if
you right even if you ask him from מסכת כלה Masechet Kallah
which is a small מסכת masechet that is a little bit obscure.
Nevertheless you can ask him any question and he'll know the answer.
Okay so what's this got
to do with being a פרנס? parnas? So I said פרנס parnas
here I
don't think means a lay leader means a rabbinic leader. Okay okay
so anyway so that's what גמרא Gemara says.
The גמרא Gemara continues actually תוספות Tosfos tries to limit that because
we'll see later that the גמרא Gemara does not have such extreme
standards and תוספות Tosfos tries to say no no no it means
you can ask him in his area of expertise. Even his area
of expertise is something so small as כלה. Kallah. כלה Kallah is
one פרק perek it's only like tannaitic material there's no גמרא Gemara
on it it's a very easy it's basically talks about the שבע
ברכות sheva brachot and other things associated with the wedding. So so
תוספות Tosfos tries to like reverse this based on the גמרא Gemara
that we're going to come up later in another גמרא. Gemara. It
doesn't mean he knows everything from A to Z it means he
has expertise in one area even if it's only a relatively small
area.
So he's an expert in ואפילו במסכת
כלה
va'afilu
b'masechet
kallah but you can ask
him כלה kallah and he'll get it right?
Exactly you can ask him שבע ברכות sheva brachot questions. Okay so
anyway that's a
quite radical different interpretation.
It sounds more like the first way I said which is רש"י
Rashi's read. Okay now the גמרא Gemara continues ואמר רבי יוחנן v'amar
Rabbi Yochanan said Rabbi Yochanan איזהו תלמיד חכם שבני עירו מצווים לעשות
לו מלאכתו eizehu talmid chacham she-b'nei iro metzuvim la'asot lo melachto what
is the Torah sage that the here you go Rivka that the
people of the town are obligated to actually you know provide for
him do his work for him so he can dedicate himself to
his learning and his study and so on? זה שמניח חפצו ועוסק
בחפצי שמים. ze she-maniach cheftzo v'osek b'cheftzei shamayim. Somebody who completely abandons
his own pursuits and just devotes himself purely to to heavenly pursuits.
והני מילי למפשט בריפתא v'hani mili le-mipshat b'riftah but even that is
only to provide bread. Doesn't mean you have to give him a
nice house doesn't mean you have to give him fancy food to
provide him his basic sustenance. What והני מילי למפשט בריפתא? v'hani mili
le-mipshat b'riftah? What? בריפתא? b'riftah? I know exactly yeah. Yeah I know.
And look this is a much larger discussion you know the רמב"ם
Rambam already came out very very vigorously against the whole phenomenon of
כולל kollel and people supporting people who sit and learn you know
he mentioned how many of all of חז"ל Chazal had professions you
know you don't see that they were supported by the ציבור. tzibbur.
Of course this idea of supporting people so they could devote themselves
you know was was a long-standing practice in various communities. The רמב"ם
Rambam was particularly responding because he felt that people were sort of
compelled you know
by social pressures to donate to that support
even though you know and that he really saw this as a
very negative phenomenon because of all the you know there's a lot
of bad parts to that. And again I think that some of
us would feel the same way a community we you know like
like graduate schools you know you pay to go to medical school
or you know or law school but if you want to study
you know Chinese art then you'll get a PhD. You know, then
you usually get, you know, you get a fellowship, get paid to
do it because the society believes that there's some things like the
liberal arts, מדעי הרוח Madaei HaRuach as it would be called in
Hebrew, that we should invest in people, you know, becoming scholars in
that that are not remunerative and we want to help support that.
And I think that most people would not mind that for particular
individuals, you know, that really are deserving of it and that will
have a very serious selection
process, that they deserve to
be supported by the community, either because of their scholarship or because
of the leadership that they'll provide. But you know, the problem is,
the question is, when it becomes very widespread and institutionalized and so
on. What? מדעי הרוח Madaei HaRuach until they apply? Right, although some
people might deserve to be lifelong scholars, you know, Einstein in the
Institute of Advanced Studies in Princeton or whatever, but nevertheless again, that's
if you have a very high selection process. Anyway, but I do
want to say that it says מניח חפצו ועוסק בחפצי שמים, maniach
cheftzo ve'osek becheftzei Shamayim, you know, could be read to say that
anybody that learns, if you're a תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, of course
you're spending your hours learning. It means you don't do anything else,
like you never leave the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, you know, that
could be what that could be part of what the גמרא's Gemara
trying to emphasize. But anyway, this does tap into a much larger
debate around these issues. It describes the רמב"ם Rambam too
if you read this גמרא Gemara and the רמב"ם.
Rambam. You know whatever, there are always sources on both sides. You
can look at the debates around the רמב"ם. Rambam. ואמר רבי יוחנן,
Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, and said Rabbi Yochanan, איזהו תלמיד חכם, eizehu Talmid
Chacham, who is a תלמיד חכם? Talmid Chacham? So we'll see in
a minute for what purposes we've been talking about different purposes for
which you're defined as a תלמיד חכם. Talmid Chacham. כל ששואלין אותו
הלכה בכל מקום ואומרה, kol she'shoalin oto halacha bechol makom ve'omrah, similarly
like we said before, you can ask him a הלכה halacha from
anywhere and he can tell you. למאי נפקא מינה, lemai nafka mina,
but for what purposes is it important to categorize him as a
תלמיד חכם? Talmid Chacham? למינויי פרנס על הציבור leminuyei parnas al hatzibur
to appoint him as, like we said before, as a leader over
the congregation, presumably a rabbinic leader. And now the גמרא Gemara qualifies
what it said before, and you'll see where תוספות's Tosafot comment was
coming from. אי בחדא מסכתא, ei bechada masechta, if he is a
master of one tractate, so you know, I studied שבת. Shabbat. You
can ask me any question in הלכות שבת. Hilchot Shabbat. Any other
thing, don't ask me, or I'll have to get back to you,
but הלכות שבת Hilchot Shabbat you can ask me anything. Then באתריה,
be'asreih, you can appoint him as a rabbinic leader in his place,
like a local rabbinic leader. אי בכולה תנויי, ei bechulah tenuyei, if
he's like, you know, if he's knowledgeable in like everything, you can
ask me anywhere from ש"ס, Shas, any area of הלכה, halacha, then
בריש מתיבתא, bereish metivta, then you can actually make him like a
ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, like not just a local one but a
more regional, right authority. Right, what? That's interesting. There are the ones
who are saying that that's the focus because each one learned a
different מסכתא. masechta. No, no, that's a myth, that idea. Okay, but
there's a myth that, whatever, I don't want to say. Anyway, but
okay, moving on. רבי שמעון בן לקיש אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish
omer, אלו כלים האוליירין הבאין ממדינת הים. elu keilim ha'ulyarin haba'in mimedinat
hayam. Now back to the whole דרשה drasha we said way before,
the whole discussion before about clothes. Right, oh, right, right, right. What
were these workers' clothes that even on
one side is a stain? So we said it meant תלמידי חכמים,
Talmidei Chachamim, and then we had a whole digression about תלמידי חכמים.
Talmidei Chachamim. So he's going back to the clothes that one side
of a stain is a problem. So he says, אלו כלים האוליירין
הבאין ממדינת הים, elu keilim ha'ulyarin haba'in mimedinat hayam, these are like
the bath attendants' garments, like רש"י Rashi might say, like a, maybe
a particular like robe that you put on right after you get
out of the bath, that come from overseas and they're very, you
know, you're very מקפיד makpid on how they look, and even one
stain is like, especially you come out of the bath, you want
your clothes to look very clean. Anyway, even one stain is a
problem, even on
one side is a problem.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, למימרא דחיורי נינהו, lemeimra dechivari ninhu,
presumably you're saying that they're white, because that's the way stains would
show up as opposed to if they were dark-colored. והאמר להו רבי
ינאי לבניו, veha'amar lehu Rabbi Yannai levanav, and didn't Rabbi Yannai say
to his children, בני, banai, my sons, אל תקברוני לא בכלים לבנים
ולא בכלים שחורים, al tikberuni lo becheilim levanim velo becheilim shechorim, don't
bury me in white clothes or in black clothes. לבנים, levanim, white
clothes, שמא לא אזכה ואהיה כחתן בין אבלים, shema lo ezkeh ve'ehyeh
kechatan bein avelim, white clothes because maybe I won't merit and I'll
go to גיהנום, Gehinnom, and I'll be looking like a bridegroom, you
know, amongst mourners. Everybody will be in black in גיהנום Gehinnom and
I'll be white, and you know, even if I'm going to גיהנום,
Gehinnom, I don't want, I want to be dressed appropriately. לבנים? levanim?
So שחורים, shechorim, not in black clothes, שמא אזכה ואהיה כאבל בין
חתנים, shema ezkeh ve'ehyeh ke'avel bein chatanim, because maybe I'll merit and
be, go up to heaven and then I'll look like a mourner
amongst the grooms. אלא, ela, very interesting, right, the image, sort of
like this popular image based on how you're dressed, that's how like
you'll, clothes you appear in heaven. Anyway, right, anyway, and we of
course do use white clothes. Anyway, but אלא בכלים האוליירין הבאין ממדינת
הים, ela becheilim ha'ulyarin haba'in mimedinat hayam, but by these bath, you
know, bath attendants' clothes that come from overseas. So you see they're
not white. אלמא סומקי נינהו, alma sumkei ninhu, they must be red.
I don't know how that's the alternative, but somehow, right, some other
color. גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult, הא
בגלימי הא בלבושי, ha biglimei ha belivushei, whether it's under, whether it's
the... Garments, whether your garments or whether your normal garments or the
sort of the outer garments, like the outer cloak. So the normal
garments would presumably be white, and the outer cloak would be a
darker color.
Okay, anyway, moving on, the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this. רבי
ישמעאל אומר מקפלין *Rabbi Ishmael Omer mekapalin*.
So that was a whole fascinating digression about שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat* clothes
and clothes in general, תלמידי חכמים *Talmidei Chachamim* and so on. Back
to the משנה Mishnah: *Mishnah*, which is about preparing from שבת Shabbat
*Shabbat* to יום כפור *Yom Kippur* and יום כפור *Yom Kippur* for
שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*. If you remember, there was the position of רבי
ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* says that he can prepare from יום כפור *Yom
Kippur* to שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*, but not from שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* to
יום כפור *Yom Kippur*. And רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said you can't
prepare from one to the next. So let's take a look. And
it also even dealt with burning the fats of sacrifices of one
to the next, even not even a real biblical prohibition. Can יום
כפור *Yom Kippur* serve שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*? And רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael*
said yes, and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said no. תנו רבנן *Tano
Rabbanan*, עולת שבת Shabbat, בשבתו *Olah Shabbat beShabbato*, the עולה *Olah* of
שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* in its שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*, לימד על חלבי שבת
Shabbat. שמקריבין ביום הכפורים *limed al chelvei Shabbat shemakrivin beYom HaKippurim*. So
שבת Shabbat בשבתו *Shabbat beShabbato*, you can take the עולה *Olah* for
one שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* for another שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*. That's how it's
being read. So what's another שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*? יום כפור *Yom Kippur*.
So it's the next day anyway, so that's the immediate. So if
you didn't have a chance to burn the fats of שבת Shabbat
*Shabbat*, you can burn on יום כפור *Yom Kippur*. עולת שבת *Olah
Shabbat* for the following, for another שבת *Shabbat*. So יכול אף של
יום הכפורים בשבת *yakhol af shel Yom HaKippurim beShabbat*, maybe even do
it the other way around. תלמוד לומר בשבתו *Talmud lomar beShabbato*. No,
only in its שבת *Shabbat*, which is limiting. So you have to
choose only one way, and obviously we read even though in some
ways the תורה *Torah*, certainly in most people's mindset יום כפור *Yom
Kippur* is the holiest day of the year. It's called שבת שבתון
*Shabbat Shabbaton*, right? It's a double שבת *Shabbat*. It's a שבת *Shabbat*
from מלאכה *melacha* and it's a שבת *Shabbat* from eating and drinking
and physical pleasures. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands that the קדושה
kedusha. *kedusha* of the weekly שבת *Shabbat* is higher because it's חייב
מיתה *chayav mita* demonstrated by the punishment if you violate it. It's
the death penalty, whereas by יום כפור *Yom Kippur* it's כרת *kares*.
So therefore, if we have to choose, we'll say יום כפור *Yom
Kippur* serves שבת *Shabbat* and not the other way around. דברי רבי
ישמעאל *Divrei Rabbi Ishmael*. That's what רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* says. רבי
עקיבא אומר עולת שבת בשבתו *Rabbi Akiva Omer Olah Shabbat beShabbato*. No,
we emphasize בשבתו *beShabbato*. Each שבת *Shabbat* can only serve itself. לימד
על חלבי שבת שמקרבין ביום טוב *limed al chelvei Shabbat shekravin beYom
Tov*. Now what they could be done is that they can be
brought on a יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* that follows שבת
*Shabbat*. Okay, שמקרבין ביום טוב *shekravin beYom Tov*. יכול אף ביום הכפורים
*yakhol af beYom HaKippurim*, maybe even it could be brought on יום
כפור *Yom Kippur*. תלמוד לומר בשבתו *Talmud lomar beShabbato*, only in its
שבת *Shabbat*. So somehow he reads the שבת בשבת *Shabbat beShabbat* that
it could be done for some other day that is a sanctified
day, but he really emphasizes the ו *vav* in a much more
limiting way and therefore only if it's something like יום כפור *Yom
Kippur* or שבת *Shabbat*, those you cannot one cannot serve the other.
Only יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* can serve שבת *Shabbat*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to try to unpack this. כשתמצא
לומר *keshetimtza lomar*, if you want you could say. By the way,
the flip of יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* serving שבת *Shabbat*,
here we're talking about יום כפור *Yom Kippur* and יום טוב Yom
Tov. *Yom Tov* following שבת *Shabbat* and burning the fats and serving
it sort of after the fact. But the emphasis in the משנה
*Mishnah* was can you prepare on יום כפור *Yom Kippur* for שבת
*Shabbat*? And we have this by יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*
all the time, right? You make ערוב תבשילין *Eruv Tavshilin* and you
absolutely can cook on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* for שבת
*Shabbat*, even it's a biblical cooking. So the idea of יום טוב
Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* preparing for שבת *Shabbat*, that's what רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva* is saying. That we learn out of the פסוק *pasuk*,
not יום כפור *Yom Kippur* but יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*,
yes. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. כשתמצא לומר
*keshetimtza lomar*, if you want you could say. לדברי רבי ישמעאל נדרים
ונדבות *ledivrei Rabbi Ishmael nedarim u'nedavot*, here's what they debate. לדברי רבי
ישמעאל נדרים ונדבות קרבים ביום טוב *ledivrei Rabbi Ishmael nedarim u'nedavot krevim
beYom Tov*. According to רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Ishmael* normally you could bring
free will sacrifices on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because even though there's
parts of that that are not directly about feeding you, it's burning
the fats etc., nevertheless that's acceptable because A, just because it's a
way of that you actually derive benefit even though it has these
attendant parts, so it is אוכל נפש *ochel nefesh*, and B, maybe
actually it's just that's a legitimate thing to be done regardless, bringing
a קרבן *korban* even if it's not demanded, that's something you can
do on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So if that's true that already
we know that certain things could be done on יום טוב *Yom
Tov* קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot* related, and we have yet another פסוק *pasuk*
that says that something can serve שבת *Shabbat*. We don't need it
to tell us יום טוב *Yom Tov*, that we already take for
granted. You can even bring a נדר *neder* on יום טוב *Yom
Tov*. פשיטא קרא ליום הכפורים *pishikrei leYom HaKippurim*. So if the פסוק
*pasuk* is coming to say that something can serve שבת *Shabbat*, certainly
יום טוב *Yom Tov* goes without saying, so it must be saying
even יום כפור *Yom Kippur*. לדברי רבי עקיבא *ledivrei Rabbi Akiva*, according
to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* we could say נדרים ונדבות אין קרבין
ביום טוב *nedarim u'nedavot ein krevim beYom Tov*. No, a normal קרבן
*korban* you can't bring on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, so I would
not have assumed you could burn the fats of שבת *Shabbat* on
יום טוב *Yom Tov*. פשיטא קרא מאישי ביום טוב *pishikrei me’ishey beYom
Tov*. So therefore you need a פסוק *pasuk* and don't get up
to יום כפור *Yom Kippur*, first you have to just say יום
טוב *Yom Tov* is okay. אמר רבי זירא *amar Rabbi Zeira*, said
רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*, כי הוינא בבבל *ki havina beVavel*, when I
was in בבל *Vavel*, הוינא אמרי *havina amri*, I used to say
הא דתניא *ha de’tanya*, that which we taught in the ברייתא *Baraita*,
יום הכפורים שחל להיות ערב שבת לא תוקעין ומוצאי שבת לא מבדילין
mavdilin *Yom HaKippurim shechal lihyot erev Shabbat lo tokin u'motza’ei Shabbat lo
mavdilin*. If יום כפור *Yom Kippur* fell out on a Friday, again
this was before the calendar was fixed so it could happen if
What? You said it's not talking about the שופר shofar *shofar* blowing
after יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*? No, no, no. No. So
if יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, however, was ערב שבת *Erev
Shabbat*, they wouldn't blast the שופר shofar. *shofar* on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur *Yom Kippur* to say stop doing מלאכה *melacha*, שבת *Shabbat* is
coming. Everybody's already not doing מלאכה *melacha*. Okay, so לא יתקעו *lo
yetak'u*. ומוצאי שבת *u'motzei Shabbat*, if יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*
was on Sunday, לא יבדילו *lo yavdilu*. You wouldn't do הבדלה havdalah
*havdalah* between שבת *Shabbat* and יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*. Now
again, you say of course, but no, you do like a, you
know, a הבדלה havdalah *havdalah* between שבת *Shabbat* and a יום טוב
*Yom Tov* of a lesser קדושה kedusha. *kedusha*, but here you would
not because they're basically the same קדושה *kedusha*, the same prohibition of
מלאכה *melacha*, even though there's a slight difference of the עונש *onish*.
So you would not have to do the separations between the two
days, it's all the same. Okay, so I used to think but
don't you do הבדלה havdalah. *havdalah* בין קודש לקודש bein kodesh l'kodesh
*bein kodesh le-kodesh*? Right, but at least you do הבדלה havdalah *havdalah*.
You don't do it, you well, you never have שבת *Shabbat* and
יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*. Right, you do it between two
יום טובים *Yom Tovim*, between like יום טוב ראשון *Yom Tov rishon*
and יום טוב שני *Yom Tov sheni*, but that's only דרבנן d'rabbanan
*d'rabbanan* יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Anyway, fine. We don't have this reality
anyway. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara... *Gemara* says, I used to think
תיבעי דכולי *tibaye d'kolay*, that everybody would agree to that. כי סלקית
להתם *ki salkit l'hatam*, even רבי עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva* and רבי ישמעאל
*Rebbi Ishmael*, even though they're debating can יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom
Kippur* serve שבת *Shabbat* or not, that's like a very, very, you
know, marginal issue. It's not enough to make קידוש *kiddush* or הבדלה
havdalah, *havdalah* for, to make a תקיעה tekiah *tekiah* or הבדלה *havdalah*
for to indicate some difference. כי סלקית להתם *ki salkit l'hatam*, when
I made עליה *aliyah* there to ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, אשכחתיה ליהודה
בריה דרבי שמעון בן פזי *ashkechteih le'Yehuda brei d'Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi*,
I found יהודה *Yehuda* the son of רבי שמעון בן פזי *Rebbi
Shimon ben Pazi*, דיתיב וקאמר *d'yasiv ve-ka-amar*, who was sitting and saying:
רבי עקיבא היא *Rebbi Akiva hi*, that's only רבי עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva*
who says that יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* can never do
anything to serve שבת *Shabbat*. ואי רבי ישמעאל *ve'ee Rebbi Ishmael*, if
it's רבי ישמעאל *Rebbi Ishmael*, כיון דאמר חלבי שבת קריבים ביום הכיפורים
*kivan d'amar chelvei Shabbat krevim b'Yom HaKippurim*, since he says you can
bring the fats of שבת *Shabbat* on יום הכיפורים *Yom HaKippurim*, ליתקע
*litka*, so when שבת *Shabbat* leads into יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom
Kippur*, you should do a תקיעה tekiah *tekiah*. So then he says
a תקיעה tekiah *tekiah*, not a הבדלה *havdalah*, but okay, you should
do a תקיעה tekiah *tekiah*, כי היכי דליהוי ידיע דחלבי שבת קריבים
ביום הכיפורים *ki heichi d'lehavai yedia d'chelvei Shabbat krevim b'Yom HaKippurim*, so
that you could say, oh, okay, now there's something different between this,
it's יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*, maybe it's a little lesser
קדושה *kedusha*, I can bring the קרבן *korban* fats. So because there's
a slight difference, you should have done something to distinguish them. אתניסו
בהא *atnisu be'ha*, that's what they told me in ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael*. And I said back to them: No, כהנים Kohanim, זריזים הם
*kohanim zrizim hem*. No, כהנים *kohanim* are very careful, they don't, and
not only careful, actually they're very knowledgeable, they don't need a שופר
*shofar* blast to tell them this הלכה *halacha*. The שופר *shofar* blast
would only be for something for more, something that's relevant for the
larger public. סא אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב אשי
*so amar lei Mar Kushisha brei d'Rav Chisda l'Rav Ashi*, so מר
קשישא *Mar Kushisha* said to רב אשי *Rav Ashi*: מי אמרינן כהנים
זריזים הם *mi amrinan kohanim zrizim hem*, do we really say that
the כהנים *kohanim* are aware of these issues and don't need שופר
*shofar* blasts to remind them that there's like some change coming up?
והתנן *ve-hatan*, but we taught: שלוש להבדיל את העם ממלאכה *shalosh le-havdil
es ha-am mi-melacha*, three שופר *shofar* blasts to tell people stop working,
start coming in from the field; שלוש להבדיל בין קודש לחול *shalosh
le-havdil bein kodesh le-chol*, and three to say it's actually שבת *Shabbat*
now, stop doing מלאכה *melacha* altogether. And these were blasts that were
done in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. So if they're done in
the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, presumably the כהנים *kohanim* need the blasts
as well. So that's like an easy answer. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says: No, כדאמר אביי לשאר עמא דבירושלים *k'amar Abaye l'sha'ar ama d'vi-Yerushalayim*.
It might be being done in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, but
it was to serve all the people of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So הכא
נמי לשאר עמא דבירושלים *hacha nami l'sha'ar ama d'vi-Yerushalayim*, here too, it
was done for everybody else, but it's not the כהנים *kohanim* don't
need these blasts to tell them, oh, there's this difference between שבת
*Shabbat* and יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and now it's יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*, there's a slight different הלכה *halacha*. What was אביי'ס *Abaye's* statement?
אביי'ס *Abaye's* statement was not about this, it was like אביי *Abaye*
says in a different context. It was talking about הלני המלכה *Helni
HaMalka* made this gold מנורה *menorah* in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*,
and when the sun shone on it in a certain way and
it sort of, you know, it shone in a particular way, you
knew that it was time to say the שמע *Shema*. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says: Yeah, but the כהנים *kohanim* say the שמע *Shema*
before sunrise. So it's alright, it was for everybody else, לשאר עמא
דבירושלים *l'sha'ar ama d'vi-Yerushalayim*. So here too, it was to serve everybody
else, it wasn't for their needs. All right. Well it would make
sense if the כהנים *kohanim* are so knowledgeable that they would be
the ones to sound it for everybody. Exactly. Exactly. Okay. Now the
גמרא *Gemara* ends this whole discussion about שבת *Shabbat* and יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur* with a fascinating like little point which says the one
thing that we allow on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* that we don't
allow on שבת *Shabbat* is called... is the thing we're going to
see see called... כניבת ירק knivat yerek *knivas yerek*, stripping... like... stripping,
what's it called? Not peeling, when you remove like the leaves... it's
called stripping, anyway, whatever it is, vegetables, anyway, so it's like removing
the leaves from vegetables... trimming. Thank you, trimming. Trimming vegetables. So that's
something we don't allow for שבת *Shabbat*. Not even clear why we
don't allow for שבת *Shabbat*. It's some type of a דרבנן *d'rabbanan*.
And we allow it for יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* towards the end
of the day. Why do we allow it towards the end of
the day? Because... so presumably right, so the thing is, the גמרא
*Gemara* says מפני עגמת נפש agmas nefesh. *mipnei agmas nefesh*, which you
assume means and some do interpret to mean that, you know, it's
getting to the end of the day, that if you can prepare
a little bit of food, it gets you feeling a little bit
calmer. and it being ready and so on, so it's to help
address the עגמת נפש. רש״י Rashi interestingly says the opposite. It's to
help increase the עגמת נפש. It gets you, it whets your appetite.
But anyway, it was a particular thing they allowed on יום כיפור.
So since we're talking about the relationship of יום כיפור to שבת,
we're now going to talk about this issue of כניבת ירק knivat
yerek. when the two days are either juxtaposed or are on the
same day. What's the איסור? issur? Yeah, it's some rabbinic thing, maybe
it's a type of like a בורר borer or maybe a type
of... Okay, so they allowed it. First of all, the thing to
be aware of about הכנה, hachana, as I said before, is we
have this perception, any form of preparation is forbidden. And for the
ראשונים, Rishonim, they often phrase it as you can't be טורח toreach
on שבת לצורך חול. l'tzorech chol. Okay, so טורח toreach is a
more limiting word. But anyway, so fine, that was part of what
they allowed. Okay, yes, Charlie. I have a question back to the
issue of the קרבנות, korbanot the free will offerings on יום טוב.
Yeah. We're required to bring things that are like free will offerings,
the חגיגה Chagigah offerings. Yeah, that's obligatory. But then at the very
end of the קרבנות passage that we read on the festivals, it
says... Yeah, bring them on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. That's the question.
Yeah, bringing it over the רגל, regel, but on חול המועד, Chol
HaMoed, not necessarily on יום טוב itself. Yeah. Okay, so now the
גמרא, so now to the end of the פרק, perek, for the
rest of the day, it's going to be this issue of כניבת
ירק. Let's take a look. Okay, so the גמרא says like this.
אבלי תיקא, A'vlitka, why didn't you do a תקיעה tekiah between שבת
and יום כיפור כי היכי דלידע דשרי בכניבת ירק, ki heichi d'leida
d'sharei b'knivat yerek, that you should know, okay, it's יום כיפור, forget
the burning of the fats or whatever, it's only relevant for the
כהנים, but because it's a slightly different קדושת יום כיפור, kedushat Yom
Kippur, when it gets to the end of the day you'll be
able to trim your vegetables. מן המנחה ולמעלה. min hamincha u'lemala. Alright,
from מנחה mincha on. So אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, אמר
רב יוסף, said Rav Yosef, לפי שאין דוחים שבות להתיר. lefi she'ein
dochin shevut l'hatir. First of all, to blow a שופר on שבת
or יום כיפור is an איסור דרבנן. issur d'rabbanan. So we would
not violate an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan to tell you you're allowed
to, you know, to do something which is an איסור דרבנן. issur
d'rabbanan. Okay? So trimming vegetables was normally an איסור דרבנן. issur d'rabbanan.
We allowed it certainly for לצורך חול. tzorech chol. We allowed it
on יום כיפור. We're not going to do a one violation to
allow this, to allow this. ורב ששת בריה דרב אידי אמר, v'Rav
Sheshet brei deRav Idi amar, שבות קרוב התירו שבות רחוק לא התירו.
shevut karov hitiru shevut rachok lo hitiru. No, there's a difference. If
it were something that would immediately change your יום כיפור, that would
be a difference right at the transition from שבת to יום כיפור,
we would blow the שופר. But here the difference will only come
at the end of the day and therefore that's not something that
we're going to do and signify by at that moment of transition
between שבת and יום כיפור. To tell people to allow it immediately?
Yeah, that's true. Okay, ושבות קרוב התירו, ve'shevut karov hitiru, would you
really say that you would do a תקיעה tekiah. in order to
indicate that some type of a דרבנן was מותר? mutar? והתניא, ve'hatanya,
it's taught in the משנה: יום טוב שחל להיות ערב שבת, Yom
Tov she'chal lihyot erev Shabbat, יום טוב that leads into שבת, תוקעין
ולא מבדילין. tokin velo mavdilin. You do a תקיעה tekiah because, you
know, it's about to be שבת and obviously there are a lot
of things that are אסור דאורייתא assur d'Oraita on שבת that are
not on יום טוב. And you wouldn't make הבדלה because you're going
to a higher level of קדושה. מוצאי שבת, Motzaei Shabbat, if יום
טוב falls on Sunday, then מבדילין and you do הבדלה בין קודש
לקודש because you're going to a lower קדושה. ולא תוקעין, velo tokin,
you don't do a תקיעה tekiah because you would not do because,
you know, because יום טוב is not more אסור assur than שבת.
So the גמרא says, ואמאי, ve'amai, why is that? ליתקע כי היכי
דלידע דשרי בשחיטה לאלתר. letka ki heichi d'leida d'sharei bi'shchita l'altar. Why
don't you do a תקיעה tekiah so people know that you can
actually do something right away now? You can do שחיטה, shchita, you
can put food on the fire. אלא, ela, so you see that
even if it was something that was immediately allowed, we don't do
תקיעה. tekiah אלא מחוורתא כדרב יוסף, ela mechuvarata k'deRav Yosef, it's better
like רב יוסף Rav Yosef that said that we don't do תקיעה
tekiah. at all to allow things. Meaning what רב יוסף Rav Yosef
is basically saying is, if you think about it, right, because this
whole thing is weird, why don't we do תקיעה tekiah to allow,
tell people you can trim the things? Normally, what do you do
to tell people, תקיעה's tekiah told to tell people on a normal
שבת what? Stop. Yeah, תקיעה's tekiah to stop. If you want to
say go, essentially, you do הבדלה. Okay? But the point is, הבדלה
isn't making an announcement, right? So if you're going from שבת to
יום כיפור, the question was let's try to announce to people that
there's a difference. Well, you don't announce it by making הבדלה, you
announce it by doing תקיעה. tekiah So that's introducing a new idea,
use a תקיעה tekiah. to say something is מותר. mutar. So the
first answer is no, we don't do תקיעות tekioat to say מותר.
mutar. Now of course, it also framed it as because doing the
תקיעה on שבת is an איסור דרבנן, issur d'rabbanan, but part of
the point is we don't do תקיעות tekioat to say מותר. mutar.
Okay, the other answer is no, we would use that, but it's
too distant. So the גמרא then demonstrates that we don't do תקיעות
tekioat to say מותר mutar because when שבת goes to יום טוב,
why don't you do a תקיעה to tell people you can put
food on the fire, you can start שחיטה? shchita? So you see
that certainly if it's a time we don't do תקיעות tekioat to
make this announcement that things are מותר. mutar. We do תקיעות tekioat
to say אסור, assur, especially if doing the תקיעה is an איסור
דרבנן issur d'rabbanan because it's over שבת or יום טוב when generally
you're not allowed to do a תקיעה. Okay, so now the גמרא...
The גמרא *Gemara* continues. Okay. אמר רב זירא *Amar Rav Zeira*, said
רב זירא *Rav Zeira*, אמר רב הונא *Amar Rav Huna*, אמר רב
יהודה *Amar Rav Yehuda*, אמר רב אמי *Amar Rav Ami*, אמר רב
הונא *Amar Rav Huna*, יום כיפור שחל להיות בשבת *Yom Kippur shechal
lihyos b'Shabbos*. Now let's say יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* falls out on
שבת *Shabbos*. Would they still allow this trimming of the vegetables? Okay,
so it says like this: אסור בקניבת ירק *assur b'knivas yereq*, you're
not allowed to trim the vegetables because of the שבת *Shabbos* part
of it. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says: אמר רב מנא *Amar
Rav Mana*, תנא מתני ברייתא *tanna matni Braisa*, מנין ליום כיפור שחל
להיות בשבת שאסור בקניבת ירק *minayin l'Yom Kippur shechal lihyos b'Shabbos she'assur
b'knivas yereq*? How do you know, first I'd like to know how
do you know you can't do קניבת ירק *knivas yereq* on שבת
*Shabbos*, but okay, how do you know when יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
falls out on שבת *Shabbos* that even then you can't do this
קניבת ירק *knivas yereq*? תלמוד לומר שבתון שבות *Talmud lomar Shabbaton Shevus*.
So it says it is a full day of rest, but it
uses the double language, so we know יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* has
that double language. So למה *l'ma*, why is it telling me this
is a day of rest? אילימא למלאכה *ileima l'melacha*, just don't do
מלאכה *melacha*, וכתיב לא תעשה כל מלאכה *v'kasiv lo sa'aseh kol melacha*,
I know that. אלא לקניבת ירק *ella l'knivas yereq*, it must be.
Everybody, of course it's an אסמכתא *asmachta*. Look at תוספות *Tosfos*: אלא
לקניבת ירק נראה לי דאסמכתא בעלמא הוא דאי דאורייתא ביום כיפור נמי
לצורך *ella l'knivas yereq nireh li d'asmachta b'alma hu d'im d'Oraisa b'Yom
Kippur nami l'tzorech*, but obviously it's going to be אסור *assur* on
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* if it's דאורייתא *d'Oraisa*. So it's an אסמכתא
*asmachta*. So it's funny, so anyway but the point is, and somehow
because of the double language of שבתון שבות *Shabbaton Shevus*, so even
when it falls out on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. שמע מינה *shma
mina*, that's a good proof. אמר רב חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן *Amar Rav Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan*, יום כיפור שחל
להיות בשבת מותר בקניבת ירק *Yom Kippur shechal lihyos b'Shabbos muttar b'knivas
yereq*. No, you're allowed to. It's so fun of a big debate
how many how much time is given, airspace is given to this
question of trimming vegetables, you know, anyway, but when יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur* falls on שבת *Shabbos*. Anyway, מתיבי *meiseivei*, they're asking: מנין ליום
כיפור שחל להיות בשבת שאסור בקניבת ירק *minayin l'Yom Kippur shechal lihyos
b'Shabbos she'assur b'knivas yereq*? What we just talked before. תלמוד לומר שבתון
שבות *Talmud lomar Shabbaton Shevus*. למאי *l'mai*? אילימא למלאכה וכתיב לא תעשה
כל מלאכה *ileima l'melacha v'kasiv lo sa'aseh kol melacha*. אלא לקניבת ירק
*ella l'knivas yereq*. So you see that whole דרשה *drasha* assumes that
you can't do it when it falls out on שבת *Shabbos*. גמרא
*Gemara* says לא לעולם למלאכה *lo l'olam l'melacha*. No, the idea of
שבתון שבות *Shabbaton Shevus* is not telling you this new thing of
קניבת ירק *knivas yereq*, either as an אסמכתא *asmachta* or whatever, it's
telling you just don't do מלאכה *melacha* on שבת *Shabbos*. So why
do you need that? You already have a פסוק *pasuk* that says
don't do מלאכה *melacha* on שבת *Shabbos*. לאו בלאו ועשה ולא תעשה
*lav b'lav v'aseh v'lo sa'aseh*. Okay, to tell you that there's both
a negative and a positive to not doing מלאכה *melacha* on שבת
*Shabbos*. Don't do מלאכה *melacha*, what? Rebbe, wouldn't say that קניבת ירק
*knivas yereq*? I know, everybody says it's an עשה *aseh* by שבת
*Shabbos*. Anyway, תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן *tanya k'vosei d'Rabbi Yochanan*, מתניא דרבי
יוחנן *mitanya d'Rabbi Yochanan*, יום כיפור שחל להיות בשבת *Yom Kippur shechal
lihyos b'Shabbos*, if יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* falls on a שבת *Shabbos*,
מותר בקניבת ירק *muttar b'knivas yereq*, you can trim your vegetables. Okay,
let's skip the parentheses. מפציעין באגוזים ומפרכסין ברימונים מן המנחה ולמעלה *maftzin
b'egozim umfarchisin b'rimonim min hamincha u'l'ma'ala*. Not only that, maybe this is
even when it's on שבת *Shabbos* or certainly on a normal יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur*, you can also start cracking nuts and removing pomegranate
seeds starting from מנחה *mincha* time. From מנחה *mincha* time and on,
מפני אגמת נפש *mipnei agmas nefesh*, because of אגמת נפש *agmas nefesh*.
Now again רש"י *Rashi* says it's increase אגמת נפש *agmas nefesh*. If
you look at the side it says: פירוש שלא יהא טורח במוצאי
היום בקניבה ותהא נפשו אגומה לעשות *pirush shelo yehei torech b'motza'ei Hayom
b'kniva v'tehei nafsho aguma la'asos*. So you won't have to be spending
time after יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and extending the fast unnecessarily. וכן
בפצוע אגוזים *v'chen b'pitzu'a egozim* etc. etc. Okay. דבי רב יהודה מקנבי
כרבא *d'vei Rav Yehuda mikanvei karva*. In the house of רב יהודה
*Rav Yehuda* on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* they would trim the, what's
כרבא *karva*, the cabbage? דבי רבא גרדי קראי *d'vei Rava garde karvei*.
In רבא *Rava*'s house they would like scrape the gourds. כיון דחזא
דהוו קא מחרפי *kivon d'chaza d'havei kama charfi*, but then he saw
people were starting to do it. By the way, דבי *d'vei*, the
house of, means the wife, probably, you know, that's normally the way
it's translated, the association of wife with house. כיון דחזא דהוו קא
מחרפי *kivon d'chaza d'havei kama charfi*, but then he saw that people
were, you know, maybe even his servants too, anyway then people saw
that they were doing it too early. They weren't waiting till מנחה
*mincha* time. So they were abusing the allowance. So אמר להו *amar
lehu*, he said to them: אתא איגרתא
ממערבא *asa
igresa mi'ma'arava*,
I
just
got
a
letter
from
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*,
משמיה דרבי
יוחנן
דאסור
*mishmei d'Rabbi
Yochanan
d'assur*,
in the
name of
רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi
Yochanan* that it's
forbidden. So
he felt
that
they were abusing
it. Well
maybe
he
did
know
that there was
a
position
that
said it
was forbidden,
okay, but
because
remember
you're,
actually
no, because
רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi
Yochanan*
says
מותר בקניבת
ירק
*muttar
b'knivas
yereq*.
Anyway,
so who knows.
So
anyway here
maybe.
Okay,
הדרן עלך ואלו
קשרים
*hadran
alach
v'eilu k'sharim*.
All right,
so starting
a
new
פרק
*perek*
tomorrow.
All right.